JITESH CHAVDA

Mechanical Engineer

An astute professional with 16 years of experience in the field of project, maintenance, operation and technical service delivery in heavy machinery in steel hot rolling mill, cold rolling mill, minerals and wind turbine generator. Deft at project management, site management, rollshop management, spares & inventory management, budgeting, cost control, feasibility study, process analysis & study.





iit_81@yahoo.co.in

iit_81@yahoo.co.in



Ahmedabad, India

+91 9925853796



in linkedin.com/in/jitesh-chavda-mechanical-engineer

WORK EXPERIENCE

Site InCharge (Project delivery) SKF INDIA LTD.

12/2015 - 05/2020

Jamshedpur, India

Responsibilities

- Responsible for project delivery of technical services to customer in metal segment - hot & cold rolling mills, with responsibility for the successful delivery of all elements, to specified level of time, budget & quality as per SLA.
- Which includes leading project teams, rectifying reliability issues, monitoring progress, tracking KPIs and managing budgets.
- Carried out feasibility study, cycle time analysis, drawing study, RCFA, MTBF, MTTR. Developed SOPs, SMPs, HIRA, safety guidelines, check sheets. Conducted ISO, OHSAS & statutory audits, skill assessment for work force, training & technology upgradation.
- Implemented best maintenance practices, maintenance planning & coordination, 5S, JIT & KAIZEN.
- Maintenance & overhaul of large bearing, rolls assy & heavy machinery.
- Supported to sales & business development team to boost business & create new business opportunities.

Manager - Mechanical maintenance BOMBAY MINERALS LTD. (ASHAPURA GROUP)

05/2015 - 11/2015

Porbandar, Gujarat

Responsibilities

- Responsible for maintenance planning, spare management, budget, cost reduction, outsource job planning for raw bauxite crushing line.
- Suggested solution & modifications based on studied production loss, machine parts failure & operating procedures.

Deputy Manager - Engrg. & Maint. HOSPET STEELS LTD.

05/2014 - 09/2014

Hospet, Karnataka

Responsibilities

 Responsible for planning & coordination, vendor quotation, material indent, purchase follow-up, supervising & monitoring of work progress as per project schedule in brownfield project of bar rolling mill - 2.

SKILLS

Critical thinking & problem solving

Teamwork & collaboration

Effective communication

Professionalism & strong work ethic

Maintenance strategy

Planning & coordination

Computer proficient

HONOR AWARDS

The best safety model exhibition (07/2016 - 10/2017) HINDALCO INDUSTRIES LTD - HIRAKUD FRP (ADITYA BIRLA)

Awarded for best safety model exhibition competition during 46th National safety week-2017 (Deputed by SKF INDIA LTD.)

ACHIEVEMENTS

COST SAVING

Cost saving of INR 10 lac by repairing the damaged labyrinth ring for 4 row CRB of back up roll at HINDALCO INDUSTRIES LTD. (HIRAKUD FRP)

QUALITY IMROVEMENT & TIME SAVING

Improved quality & time saving to 90% by designing & developing a gap setting tool for brush roll in aluminum hot rolling mill at HINDALCO INDUSTRIES LTD. (HIRAKUD FRP)

MODIFICATION

Provided a modification in mill bearing housing to minimize bearing failure & got approved from mill OEM at TATA STEEL CRM BARA at JAMSHEDPUR

CUSTOMER SATISFACTION

Achieved customer satisfaction index to 97% at TATA STEEL CRM BARA at **JAMSHEDPUR**

CERTIFICATES

ISO/TS 29001:2010 - Internal Auditor (API Spec. Q1) (11/2012)

Issued by TUV NORD (India)

ISO 9001:2008 - Internal Auditor (QMS) (12/2009) Issued by DET NORSKE VERITAS

WORK EXPERIENCE

Assistant Manager - CRM 2 project JSW STEEL LTD.

05/2013 - 05/2014

Bellary, Karnataka

Responsibilities

- Responsible for monitoring progress of Rollshop & Workshop project as per schedule of cold rolling mill project.
- Planning & coordination, quality inspection, project documentation, vendor enquiry, RFQ, indent raised for 2 years spare, purchase follow-up, house keeping & safety at project site.

Senior Engineer - OperationWELSPUN CORP LTD. (Plate & Coil Mills Division)

05/2007 - 03/2013

Anjar, Gujarat

Responsibilities

- Responsible for inspection of received drawings, equipment, spares, preparation of drawing in Auto CAD, BOM, indent raising, purchase follow-up, contractor bill verification, planning & coordination, work supervision.
- Operation & maintenance in Rollshop department which includes roll maintenance & grinding, roll assembly, servicing & overhauling of large bearing & heavy machinery. MIS report preparation for roll & spare consumption.
- Gained experience in 5S, TPM, TQM & ISO documentations.

Engineer - O & MSUZLON WINDFARM SERVICES LTD.

08/2003 - 05/2007

Kutch, Gujarat

Responsibilities

 Responsible for preventive, predictive, breakdown maintenance of wind turbine generator & updating data in SAP.

VOLUNTEER EXPERIENCE

Devotee

ISKCON - The International Society for Krishna Consciousness

12/2020 - 03/2021

Ahmedabad, India

Tasks/Achievements

- Awarded with certificate of participation for GITA SAAR 2020 (6 sessions online course on Philosophy of Bhagavad Gita).
- Played a role of Chaitanya Mahaprabhu in stage drama.
- Be a part to spread lord Shree Krishna consciousness through drama, events, Gita distribution, singing Krishna hymn, visiting communities, spiritual discussion, people counselling, fund raising, project, operation & maintenance of temple.

EDUCATION

B. E. MechanicalLalbhai Dalpatbhai College of Engineering (Gujarat university)

07/1998 - 06/2002

Ahmedabad, India

LANGUAGES

English

Hindi

Full Professional Proficiency

Full Professional Proficiency

Guiarati

Native or Bilingual Proficiency

INTERESTS

Reading books

Watching movies & series

Listening songs

Playing indoor games

Martial arts

Sketching & painting

Travelling

Cooking

New ideas

Renewable energy development